{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "Upon the declaration of this war, Ohio congressman Joshua Giddings wrote an open letter to the president outlining how this war was against an \"unoffending people\" and a thinly veiled attempt to \"safeguard slavery.\" One president was angry at a peace negotiator in this war for forgoing the acquisition of Baja California for fifteen million dollars in reparations from the government of Santa Anna. Nicholas Trist and future president José Joaquín de Herrera negotiated an end to, for ten points, what North American war, ended by the treaty of Guadeloupe Hidalgo?",
      "answer": "Mexican-American War or Intervención estadounidense en México"
    },
    {
      "question": "Nancy Pelosi tried to invoke a little-known section of this amendment that disqualifies people for office on the basis of insurrection. Oliver Wendell Holmes wrote that this amendment “does not enact Mr. Herbert Spencer’s Social Statics” in the case Lochner v. New York. It's not the Fifth Amendment, but this amendment’s Due Process Clause was used to apply the Bill of Rights to states. Griswold v. Connecticut held that this amendment established a “right to privacy.\" For ten points, name this Constitutional amendment that established the Equal Protection Clause.",
      "answer": "Fourteenth Amendment"
    },
    {
      "question": "During this event, a \"naval quarantine\" by the UN, enforced by the cruisers Essex and Gearing, failed to apprehend the Bucharest. In the wake of this event, a teletype was established between the Kremlin and the White House to have a direct line of communication. In an effort to end this conflict, an agreement to remove ballistic weapons from Greece and Turkey was drawn up. An attempt to place warheads on the title Caribbean island led to, for ten points, what 1962 \"crisis\" between the Khrushchev regime and the Kennedy administration?",
      "answer": "Cuban Missile Crisis"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man siphoned money to his family through a tax by which the ultra-wealthy were forced to donate to the Dana Sejahtera [[seh-jah-TEH-rah]] Mandiri fund. This man's ally, Ali Murtopo, incited riots to coincide with a visit by Japanese prime minister Kakuei Tanaka to discredit his rival Sumitro. The \"Supersemar\" Edict gave this general the right to restore order following a mid-1960s \"Communist Purge\" at the behest of his superior, Sukarno. The 1998 Riots in Jakarta led to the downfall of, for ten points, which dictator's \"New Order\" regime in Indonesia?",
      "answer": "Suharto 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
    },
    {
      "question": "One hoax involving this event was the made-up shooting of Martin Šmíd [[SHMEED]] by police. Protesters during this event jingled keys to signify the unlocking of doors when Miloš Jakeš [[MEE-lohsh YAH-kehsh]] resigned as General Secretary. This event began on International Students' Day and ended when Gustáv Husák resigned and was replaced with the leader of the Charter 77 movement, Václav Havel. For ten points, name this revolution in 1989 that culminated with the ending of Communist rule in Czechoslovakia.",
      "answer": [
        "Velvet Revolution or Gentle Revolution",
        "or Sametová revoluce",
        "or Nežná revolúcia"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In April 2021, this person promulgated support for a global minimum corporate tax rate. This economist postulated that paying workers more than their market value in wages increases productivity in the paper, The Fair-Wage Effort Hypothesis and Unemployment that she co-wrote with her husband, George Akerlof. In 2018, Donald Trump replaced this person in one position with Jerome Powell. For ten points, name this economist, the first female Chair of the Federal Reserve and the first female Secretary of the Treasury.",
      "answer": "Janet Yellen or Janet Louise Yellen"
    },
    {
      "question": "While representing this state, Nonpartisan League leader Lynn Frazier became the first state governor to be recalled from office. Another governor of this state, \"Wild Bill\" Langer, was convicted of defrauding the federal government by ordering state employees to donate to his party. When signing the papers to approve this state's statehood, James G. Blaine shuffled the papers with those of this state's southern neighbor. For ten points, name this Great Plains state, whose city of West Fargo hosts a recreational Old West town called Bonanzaville, USA.",
      "answer": "North Dakota"
    },
    {
      "question": "A copy of this painting was covered by a blue curtain during a Colin Powell press conference at the United Nations. 45 studies of this painting throughout its creation were photographed by the artist's wife, Dora Maar. Dagger-like tongues appear in the mouths of a screaming horse and a mother with her dead child in this painting, which was defaced with the anti-Vietnam War message \"KILL LIES ALL.\" Created following the destruction of a Basque town, for ten points, what Pablo Picasso painting is set during the Spanish Civil War?",
      "answer": "Guernica 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
    },
    {
      "question": "This author wrote essays on subjects like the \"Glory Days of Medora\" and \"The American Adventure of Louis Agassiz\" in his collection Brave Companions. This writer gained fame for his 1968 chronicle of the Johnstown Flood. An illustrated edition of a book by this man includes a recreation of a letter that George Washington penned to Martha about his commission. That book, a companion to his earlier biography of John Adams, focuses on the events at the start of the American Revolution. For ten points, name this historian who wrote 1776.",
      "answer": "David McCullough or David Gaub McCullough"
    },
    {
      "question": "One building at a university in this city features thirty-one distinct rooms themed to different cultures. The Nationality Rooms are located in an art-deco skyscraper in this city that was dubbed \"an inverted mineshaft\" by Frank Lloyd Wright. The Cathedral of Learning is located in this city whose Heinz Field replaced Three Rivers Stadium as the home for an NFL team in 2001. In this city's Frick Park, the Fern Hollow Bridge collapsed in January 2022. For ten points, name this city whose football team, the Steelers, reflects its industrial history.",
      "answer": [
        "Pittsburgh",
        "University of Pittsburgh",
        "Pittsburgh Steelers",
        "prompt on \"Pitt\" 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This U.S. state's first European settlement was the failed Spanish Jesuit Ajacán [[ah- hah-KAHN]] Mission. This colony's Treaty of 1677 allowed several tribes such as the Nottaway and the Saponi to keep and bear arms, so long as they maintained loyalty to the English Crown. A group of enslaved Africans were brought to this colony's Old Point Comfort in 1619. For ten points, name this state, the first colony in which was established by travelers on the Susan Constant, Godspeed, and the Discovery at Jamestown in 1607.",
        "answer": "Virginia"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This man's rebellion burned Jamestown in 1676 in protest of Governor William Berkeley's policies regarding frontier settlement and attacks from native tribes.",
        "answer": [
          "Nathaniel Bacon",
          "Bacon's Rebellion"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In response to an invasion along the Danube by this ruler, Mehmet II raised an army \"second in size only\" to the one that he used to conquer Constantinople. This ruler was captured by John Jiskra of Brandys under orders from Matthias Corvinus after this ruler disrespected the Ottomans by killing their messengers. This man’s brother, Mircea, was killed by the forces of John Hunyadi. The title of Voivode was held by this man, who ruled over Wallachia and was known for his use of stakes in dealing with enemies. For ten points, name this Romanian ruler who inspired a similarly named literary vampire.",
        "answer": [
          "Vlad the Impaler or Vlad Tepes",
          "or Vlad III",
          "Vlad Dracula",
          "Vlad Drăculea"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Wallachian nobles of this Slavic name were purged by Vlad the Impaler. In Russia, Peter the Great completely curtailed the power of nobles of this name.",
        "answer": [
          "Boyars or Bolyars",
          "or Boyarin"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Until 1997, this president's cabinet included a man nicknamed \"Nothing Wrong Norman,\" who formerly headed the Commercial Farmers' Union and repeatedly denied racial divisions under this man's regime. This man's government imprisoned rival Canaan Banana on sodomy charges and launched the \"drive out the trash\" movement to destroy slums. In 2017, Emmerson Mnangagwa [[meh-nahn-GAH-gwah]] overthrew this president. Presiding in a time of hyperinflation in the 2000s, for ten points, who was this longtime dictator of Zimbabwe?",
        "answer": "Robert Mugabe or Robert Gabriel Mugabe"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Mugabe was a member of what ethnic group, whose ancestors built Great Zimbabwe in the Middle Ages?",
        "answer": "Shona"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "To cover up the nature of this event, Manucher Ghorbanifar suggested justifying it by freeing hostages held by Hezbollah. This event was investigated by the Tower Commission and led to the conviction of Oliver North. This event violated the Boland Amendment and was carried out in order to support an anti-communist Nicaraguan paramilitary group. For ten points, identify this scandal that involved the Reagan administration selling arms to Ayatollah Khomeini’s government.",
        "answer": [
          "Iran-Contra Affair",
          "McFarlane Affair",
          "synonyms for \"Affair\" such as \"Scandal\""
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In Nicaragua, the Contras were a group of counter-revolutionaries opposed to this Marxist political party.",
        "answer": [
          "Sandinista National Liberation Front or Sandinistas",
          "or Frente Sandinista de Liberación Nacional",
          "FSLN"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "John Flaxman reconstructed a silver-gilted example of these objects that was on display at George IV’s coronation. Eleven copies of these objects were ordered by Numa Pompilius to divert thieves from stealing the one that fell from heaven. According to Virgil in the Aeneid, one of these objects depicts the death of Mettius Fufetius and the capture of the Sabine Women. The origin of that object of this type was given as a gift to Aeneas by Vulcan in his war against the Rutulians. For ten points, what type of object included the ancilia and the aegis, used as a tool of defense?",
        "answer": "Shields"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Hermodorus of Salamis designed what temple in Rome that housed the twelve ancilia?",
        "answer": "Temple of Mars or Aedes Martis in Circo"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A portion of this piece's manuscript that contained the words \"Quam olim da capo\" was stolen at the 1958 Brussels World's Fair. A bass soloist sings the same melody of an arpeggiated B-flat major trombone solo in this piece's \"Tuba Mirum.\" The wife of this piece's composer, Constanze [[kohn-STAHN-tse]], kept quiet about the role of Franz Xaver Süssmayr [[SOO-smy-uh]] in completing its \"Lacrimosa\" that was left mostly unfinished after its composer's 1791 death. For ten points, name this mass for the dead by the composer of The Magic Flute.",
        "answer": [
          "Mozart’s Requiem",
          "Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart’s Requiem Mass in D minor, K. 626"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The opening of Mozart's Requiem quotes which composer's The ways of Zion do mourn? A performance of this man's Music for the Royal Fireworks caused a three-hour traffic jam.",
        "answer": "George Frideric Handel 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In a 1992 book, Graham Hancock claims that this item was, for a time, held in Lake Tana. Known as the tabot in the Ge’ez language, this item is said to be housed in a building dedicated to “Our Lady Mary of Zion.\" Replicas of this item are contained in each Tewahedo Church. The Kebra Nagast notes that Menelik brought this item to Ethiopia while a counterfeit copy lies in Israel. A church in the Tigray region is said to hold this object, which contains a rod belonging to Aaron. For ten points, name this golden chest said to contain the original tablets of the Ten Commandments.",
        "answer": [
          "Ark of the Covenant or Ărōn haBrīṯ",
          "Ark of God",
          "Ark of Testimony"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A series of excavations by a group of \"British Israelites\" that aimed to find the Ark of the Covenant were carried out on which island’s Hill of Tara?",
        "answer": [
          "Ireland or Airlann",
          "or Éire"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This archipelago is mentioned in the Periplus of the Erythraean Sea as containing the island of Menuthias, which may refer to Unguja. Prior to colonization, the village of Kizimkazi was a major node of commerce in this archipelago, which was conquered by the forces of Ruy Marques. The Portuguese colonized this archipelago by building a fort on Pemba Island, which was later brought under the influence of the Sultanate of Oman. For ten points, name this archipelago in East Africa, unified in 1964 with the state of Tanganyika to form Tanzania.",
        "answer": "Zanzibar or Zinjibār"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The inhabitants of Zanzibar primarily speak which Bantu language, still spoken in much of East Africa alongside English?",
        "answer": [
          "Swahili",
          "KiSwahili"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Second Red Scare",
      "prompt": "Concerning the Second Red Scare, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Ideology it targeted, of which the Soviet Union was an advocate.",
          "answer": [
            "Communism",
            "Stalinism",
            "generously",
            "other variants",
            "specific kinds of Communism"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Wisconsin politician who claimed to have a list of \"hundreds\" of traitorous people in the U.S. government.",
          "answer": "Joseph McCarthy or Joseph Raymond McCarthy"
        },
        {
          "question": "Successor of Harry Truman who initially ignored the fear-mongering tactics of politicians.",
          "answer": "Dwight David \"Ike\" Eisenhower"
        },
        {
          "question": "FBI director who investigated his rival agency's heads at the CIA.",
          "answer": "John Edgar Hoover"
        },
        {
          "question": "Couple executed for spying on the U.S., sending nuclear weapon designs to the Soviets.",
          "answer": "Julius and Ethel Rosenberg or the Rosenbergs"
        },
        {
          "question": "Name for men like Dalton Trumbo who refused to name anti-capitalists in the entertainment industry.",
          "answer": [
            "\"Hollywood Ten\"",
            "Hollywood Blacklist"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "U.S. anti-Soviet counterintelligence effort which outed the espionage cabal known as the Cambridge Five.",
          "answer": "Venona Project"
        },
        {
          "question": "Law that criminalized advocating for the overthrow of the government, which was deemed mostly unconstitutional in Yates v. U.S..",
          "answer": "Smith Act or Alien Registration Act 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Early Roman Republic",
      "prompt": "Concerning the Early Roman Republic, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Collective class of commoners who agitated for rights.",
          "answer": [
            "Plebeians",
            "Plebs"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Early road which connected Rome to Brundisium, named for a 3rd century censor.",
          "answer": [
            "Via Appia",
            "Appian Way"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "King of Epirus who won a costly victory after he invaded the Italian mainland.",
          "answer": [
            "Pyrrhus of Epirus",
            "Pyrrhic Victory"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Final king, deposed in favor of establishing a Republican government.",
          "answer": "Tarquinius Superbus or Tarquin the Proud"
        },
        {
          "question": "Early foundation of Republican law, initially unwritten, which stated the rights and requirements of citizens.",
          "answer": "Laws of the Twelve Tables"
        },
        {
          "question": "Gallic chief who stated \"Woe to the Conquered\" while extracting tribute from Rome in 390 BC.",
          "answer": "Brennus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Embarrassing Roman loss during the Second Samnite War in which two consuls were forced to walk under a yoke after surrendering.",
          "answer": "Battle of the Caudine Forks"
        },
        {
          "question": "Patrician who supposedly single-handedly held the Pons Sublicius from Clusium, who aimed to overthrow the Republic.",
          "answer": "Publius Horatius Cocles 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Assassins",
      "prompt": "Concerning the medieval order of Assassins, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Traveler to Yuan China who coined the term \"Old Man of the Mountain\" for their leader.",
          "answer": "Marco Polo or Marco Emilio Polo"
        },
        {
          "question": "Asian Steppes empire whose sack of Alamut in the mid-13th century led to their downfall.",
          "answer": [
            "Mongol Empire or Mongolians",
            "or Mongols"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Ayyubid sultan and rival of Richard the Lionheart who was wounded by Assassins during the Third Crusade.",
          "answer": "Saladin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Cannabis-derived drug supposedly used by them and from which their name is derived.",
          "answer": [
            "Hashish",
            "Hashashin"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Catholic \"Knights\" to whom they gave tribute, named for a medical facility in Jerusalem.",
          "answer": [
            "Knights Hospitaller or Order of Knights of the Hospital of Saint John of Jerusalem",
            "Knights of St. John"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Subset of Shia Islam to which they adhered.",
          "answer": [
            "Isma'ilism",
            "Nizaris"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Founder of the order who conducted a prolonged war with the Seljuks.",
          "answer": "Hassan as-Sabbāh"
        },
        {
          "question": "De facto king of Jerusalem whom they killed during the 3rd Crusade while disguised as Christian monks.",
          "answer": [
            "Conrad of Montferrat or Conrad I",
            "or Corrado del Monferrato",
            "or Conrà ëd Monfrà 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
          ]
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An oxygen meter manufactured by Arnold O. Beckman was based on the designs that this scientist created while working as a military researcher. This scientist and his wife, Ava, were the founders of the International League of Humanists. This scientist modified the valence (20 pts)",
        "bond model and developed the concept of orbital hybridization. Winning the Nobel Peace Prize for his (10 pts)",
        "activism against a nuclear arms race, for ten points, what scientist also won the Nobel Prize in Chemistry for his work on The Nature of the Chemical Bond?"
      ],
      "answer": "Linus Pauling or Linus Carl Pauling"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Sam Mendes directed a film set in this country in which one character is stabbed to death by a downed pilot as another character seeks to fetch water. One director from this country created Captain von Rauffenstein in a film set in a prisoner-of-war camp during World War One titled (20 pts)",
        "The Grand Illusion. A Christopher Nolan film set in this country partly takes place on land, in the air, and at (10 pts)",
        "sea and chronicles the efforts of civilian boats to assist soldiers on a beach during World War Two. For ten points, name this nation, the setting of the films 1917 and Dunkirk."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Republic of France or Republique francaise",
        "or French Republic"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man was kidnapped by Thomas Hunt and subsequently sold as a slave in the city of Malaga, Spain. This man, who was the only survivor of an epidemic that wiped out his tribe, served as a translator for Edward Winslow. (20 pts)",
        "This man explained the process of growing corn and beans according to an account by William (10 pts)",
        "Bradford. For ten points, name this member of the Patuxet [[pah-TUK-set]] tribe who was present at the First Thanksgiving and assisted the Mayflower Pilgrims in establishing their colony."
      ],
      "answer": "Squanto or Tisquantum"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Elijah Coleman Bridgman was the first American missionary to this dynasty, after which he founded a Repository for this dynasty's politics and culture. Peter Parker served as a translator for a treaty between the U.S. and this dynasty negotiated by Caleb Cushing, (20 pts)",
        "in which Americans attained extraterritoriality rights. This dynasty, which signed the Treaty of Wanghia [[WAHNG-YAH]], was the subject of a doctrine by John Hay encouraging (10 pts)",
        "Western powers to keep an \"open door.\" For ten points, name this dynasty, during which American troops were sent to China to halt the Boxer Rebellion."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Qing ] Dynasty or Great Qing",
        "or Dà Qīng",
        "or Daicing gurun 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This archipelago was once believed to be a part of the continent Terra Australis. Early settlers in this archipelago include the Yaghan people. Julio Popper committed genocide against the native Selk’nam people of this archipelago. The Boundary Treaty (20 pts)",
        "of 1881 defined the border of this archipelago and divided it between two countries. Divided between (10 pts)",
        "Chile and Argentina, for ten points, what archipelago is located at the southernmost tip of South America?"
      ],
      "answer": "Tierra del Fuego"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During this war, the I-26 torpedoed Estevan Point Lighthouse in a successful bid to disrupt maritime trade. Men from one country who refused to fight overseas during this war were known as \"Zombies,\" leading to the second Conscription (20 pts)",
        "Crisis. During this war, Canadian divisions under Rod Keller were tasked with taking Juno (10 pts)",
        "Beach. The Dominion of Canada was tasked with protecting the British dominion of Newfoundland during, for ten points, what war begun by a Nazi invasion of Poland?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "World War Two",
        "Second World War"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This Justice wrote that the Constitution “did not enact Myrrdahl’s American Dilemma” to argue that the Court should stay out of segregation cases. This Justice presided over state sodomy law cases, including Romer v. Evans, in which he typically issued (20 pts)",
        "dissenting opinions. This Justice challenged Congressional extensions of the Commerce Clause in U.S. v. Lopez, breaking from his predecessor (10 pts)",
        "Warren Burger. For ten points, name this Conservative Chief Justice who was appointed by Ronald Reagan and succeeded by John Roberts."
      ],
      "answer": "William Rehnquist or William Hubbs Rehnquist"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) On national television, this politician stated \"The Republic is not a dictatorship of rumours, a dictatorship of calumny\" while dismissing his involvement in the Clearstream Affair. On Bastille Day, Unité Radicale member Maxime Brunerie (20 pts)",
        "fired at this president in his motorcade. At the site of the Vel' d'Hiv [[vehl-DEEV]] Roundup, this politician gave a speech admitting French guilt in the Holocaust. The President of France for much of the (10 pts)",
        "90s and 2000s was, for ten points, what former head of the conservative Rally for the Republic Party?"
      ],
      "answer": "Jacques Chirac or Jacques René Chirac 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
    }
  ]
}